Do you feel that communication with AI
你是否感覺到與 AI 的溝通
seems to always be separated into something?
似乎總是被分隔成某些東西？
Today, let's talk about
今天，讓我們談談
how to master such a detailed art
如何掌握這樣一門精細的藝術
to turn AI from a tool that only listens to instructions
將 AI 從一個只能聽命行事的工具
to become the strongest thinking partner around you.
變成你身邊最強大的思維夥伴。
Have you ever had this experience?
你有過這樣的經驗嗎？
It's just that you got into your mind and asked a question.
就是你腦子裡想到的，問了一個問題。
As a result, the answer given by AI
結果 AI 給出的答案
is completely wrong.
完全是錯的。
You ask Dong, he answers Qi.
你問東，他答西。
The whole thing is super speechless, right?
整個事情都超級無語，對吧？
Don't worry, you're not alone.
別擔心，你不是一個人。
The difference in communication
溝通的差異
is the core problem we're going to solve today.
是我們今天要解決的核心問題。
What should we do?
我們應該怎麼做？
The key is that
關鍵是
we have to build a communication bridge
我們必須建立一座溝通橋梁
between the ideas in your head
在你腦海中的想法
and the execution capabilities of AI.
和 AI 的執行能力之間。
And the technology to build this bridge
而建立這座橋梁的技術
is the core ability we're going to talk about today.
是我們今天要談的核心能力。
That's right, we call this core ability description.
沒錯，我們稱這個核心能力為描述。
But wait a minute,
但等等，
this is not just as simple as writing a prompt as we usually say.
這不僅僅是像我們通常說的那樣寫一個提示詞那麼簡單。
It's actually a more comprehensive communication technique
它實際上是一種更全面的溝通技巧
that allows us to accurately explain tasks to AI
使我們能夠准確地向 AI 解釋任務
and provide him with the background information he needs.
並向他提供他需要的背景信息。
Then, in the entire interaction process,
然後，在整個互動過程中，
guide him to achieve the goal we want.
引導他達到我們想要的目標。
Is it going to be difficult to master this art?
掌握這門藝術會很難嗎？
In fact, to put it bluntly,
實際上，坦率地說，
you only need to grasp three key concepts.
你只需要掌握三個關鍵概念。
Really, just these three.
真的，就這三個。
And once you understand,
一旦你理解了，
the way you interact with AI
你與 AI 互動的方式
will be completely different.
會完全不同。
Okay, what are these three pillars?
好的，這三個支柱是什麼？
They are
它們是
First, the product description of the product produced by force.
首先，由強制力生產的產品的產品描述。
Second, the process description of the guidance method.
第二，引導方法的過程描述。
And third,
第三，
this is very interesting,
這非常有趣，
the performance description of the setting atmosphere.
設定氛圍的效能描述。
As long as you cover these three pillars tightly,
只要你緊緊掌握這三個支柱，
your communication with AI will be stable.
你與 AI 的溝通就會很穩定。
Okay, let's start with the first one.
好的，讓我們從第一個開始。
How exactly do you want to accurately describe what you want?
你究竟要如何準確地描述你想要的東西？
This is the so-called product description.
這就是所謂的產品描述。
To put it simply,
簡單來說，
the ability of product description
產品描述的能力
is that you have to be able to clearly define
就是你必須能夠清楚地定義
what kind of product you want AI to create in the end.
你最終想讓 AI 創造什麼樣的產品。
Not just roughly,
不只是粗略地，
but very accurately.
而是非常準確。
How big is the difference?
差異有多大呢？
Come on, let's imagine
來吧，讓我們想像一下
you tell AI,
你告訴 AI，
hey, help me prepare dinner.
嘿，幫我準備晚餐。
This is too vague.
這太模糊了。
How does he know what you want to eat?
他怎麼知道你想吃什麼？
But if you change the way you say,
但如果你改變說法，
hey, I want to make Italian chicken noodles.
嘿，我想做義大利雞肉麵。
Give me a recipe.
給我一份食譜。
You have to have all the ingredients
你必須有所有的食材
and super detailed cooking steps on it.
和超詳細的烹飪步驟在上面。
Look, is this super clear?
看，這是不是超清楚？
This is a 100% product description.
這就是 100% 的產品描述。
So the point is,
所以重點是，
please don't let AI guess what you want.
請不要讓 AI 猜測你想要什麼。
You have to tell him clearly,
你必須清楚地告訴他，
hey, what is the background of this job?
嘿，這份工作的背景是什麼？
What do you want him to do?
你想讓他做什麼？
Make it clear step by step.
逐步說清楚。
What kind of format do you want to use in the end?
你最終想要什麼格式？
Wordang or簡報?
Word 文檔還是簡報？
Then who wants to see this thing?
那麼誰想看這個東西？
Is it for the boss or the client?
是給老闆還是客戶？
What kind of style do you want in the end?
你最終想要什麼樣的風格？
More shocking or more lively?
更震撼還是更生動？
These things have to be said clearly.
這些事情必須說清楚。
Okay, it's not enough to know what you want.
好的，僅僅知道你想要什麼是不夠的。
Sometimes more importantly,
有時候更重要的是，
how do you guide AI to do?
你如何指導 AI 去做？
This brings us to the second pillar,
這引出了第二個支柱，
the process description.
流程描述。
The process description,
流程描述，
in private,
私下裡，
is to guide AI
是指導 AI
on how to do this thing.
如何做這件事。
Remember, sometimes
記住，有時候
give AI a map,
給 AI 一張地圖，
that is, that process,
也就是說那個流程，
will be more important
會比更重要
than you just tell him the end,
你只是告訴他最終結果，
more important,
更重要，
and more efficient.
也更高效。
How to guide?
怎樣指導？
There are probably several ways.
大概有幾種方式。
You can give him a manual,
你可以給他一份手冊，
which is a guide to some major directions.
即某些主要方向的指南。
Or you can give him a recipe,
或者你可以給他一個食譜，
telling him in detail
詳細地告訴他
what to do first,
先做什麼，
what to do second.
再做什麼。
You can even show it to him in person
你甚至可以親身示範給他
and use some examples
並用一些例子
to let him learn your method.
讓他學習你的方法。
Think about it.
想一想。
Although AI's knowledge library is wide,
雖然 AI 的知識庫很廣泛，
but he doesn't know the unique situation you have.
但他不知道你所處的獨特情況。
So you can tell him
所以你可以告訴他
I have some specific information here,
我這裡有一些特定的信息，
please use these to analyze.
請用這些來分析。
Or you have to deal with these problems
或者你必須按照之後的順序
in the order after.
處理這些問題。
Or I need you to use
或者我需要你使用
a specific analysis style,
一個特定的分析風格，
or we have a standard
或者我們公司有一套標準的
working process in our company,
工作流程，
you have to follow it.
你必須遵循它。
Tell you what,
告訴你吧，
take some time to talk about these details.
花一些時間來討論這些細節。
The result will be much worse.
結果會糟糕得多。
Okay, now we come to the third,
好，現在我們談到第三點，
which is also the most
這也是最
um,
嗯，
the most delicate,
最微妙的，
the most interesting pillar.
最有趣的支柱。
How to set the atmosphere of your interaction with AI?
如何設定你與 AI 互動的氛圍？
We call it performance description.
我們稱之為性能描述。
If you can only remember one sentence in today's content,
如果你今天的內容中只能記住一句話，
then I hope it's this sentence.
那我希望就是這句話。
AI tools are not database,
AI 工具不是資料庫，
nor automatic vending machines.
也不是自動販賣機。
They are interactive systems
它們是互動系統，
that have different behavior modes
因為你給它們的不同情況
because of the different circumstances you give them.
而具有不同的行為模式。
Really, it's very similar to people.
真的，這非常像人類。
This is the most important part of performance description.
這是性能描述最重要的部分。
You have to define the behavior mode
你必須定義行為模式
when AI interacts with you.
當 AI 與你互動時。
In other words,
換句話說，
you don't just tell him what to do,
你不只是告訴它做什麼，
how to do,
如何做，
you also tell him
你還要告訴它
what role you are going to play today.
你今天要它扮演什麼角色。
So next time you open AI,
所以下次你打開 AI 時，
you can ask yourself
你可以問自己
what kind of thinking partner do I need now?
我現在需要什麼樣的思考夥伴？
Do I need a partner who will challenge me and refute me?
我需要一個會挑戰我、反駁我的夥伴嗎？
Or do I need someone who is obedient and follows me?
還是我需要一個順從並跟隨我的人？
I want him to give me super detailed information
我想要它給我超詳細的信息
or
還是
just focus on the point.
只關注重點。
I need him to explain the thinking process of each step
我需要它解釋每一步的思考過程
or just give me the answer directly.
還是直接給我答案。
You see,
你看，
these choices will create
這些選擇會創造
completely different AI partners.
完全不同的 AI 夥伴。
Okay, we've finished reading the three pillars.
好的，我們已經讀完了三個支柱。
When you combine the three descriptions
當你結合這三個描述時
of the product, process, and performance
關於你剛才提到的產品、流程和績效
that you just mentioned,
你剛才提到的
what magical things will happen?
會發生什麼神奇的事情？
The final result is
最終的結果是
you turn AI from
你把 AI 從
an assistant you know
一個你認識的助手
who is very common, like a can,
一個非常普遍的，就像罐頭一樣
into a person who is completely
轉變成一個完全的人
a person who knows you
一個認識你的人
and can help you solve those super complicated problems.
能幫你解決那些超級複雜的問題。
A super powerful tool.
一個超級強大的工具。
So this brings a question that is worth thinking about.
所以這提出了一個值得思考的問題。
After listening to these today,
聽了今天的這些內容之後
what kind of thinking partner
你想首先創造什麼樣的思考夥伴
do you want to create first?
？